<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Toastmasters | Hrakaroo</title>
    <link>/categories/toastmasters/</link>
      <atom:link href="/categories/toastmasters/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Toastmasters</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu82bb96251336236c27845c6dd2b93c07_14416_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Toastmasters</title>
      <link>/categories/toastmasters/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dance Recital</title>
      <link>/post/the-dance-recital/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/the-dance-recital/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following is the speech I wrote for the Humorous Speaking Contest
for Toastmasters.  I placed first for the Division award but had to
back out of competing at the Area level due to a travel conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This speech is intended to be performed so it is not a formal writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife, who usually took our 10 year old daughter to her dance
recitals, had been asked to speak at a conference that coincided with
a recital, so I was tasked with taking our daughter instead.  While
this might stress out some fathers, it so happened that I was an
experience dancer dad.  My work schedule was very flexible so I had
become primarily responsible for taking our daughter to her dance
classes.  I had spent hours at the dance studio and I’d seen it all.
From temper tantrums, to crying and yelling and throwing things… and
that was just the moms.  I wasn’t worried in the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first task was to take her to get her makeup for the recital.
&amp;ldquo;Black eyeliner, red lipstick.&amp;rdquo;  That seemed straightforward, but when
we got to the makeup counter we found out there isn&#39;t just one black
eyeliner.  There’s regular black, black out, onyx black, darkest
black, ferocious black and blackest black, just to name a few. I must
not be the most color aware person as all the different shades of
black looked pretty similar to me.  There were also water proof
versions of everything which I ruled out instantly as we were
certainly not going swimming.  So we eventually narrowed it down to
darkest black and blackest black, which seems like an absurd
differentiation.  I don’t know how you get to darkest without also
being the blackest but far be it from me to question a multi-billion
dollar industry.  After much back and forth we finally settled on
blackest black as we figured that way no one could complain it wasn’t
black enough.  The lipstick was a bit easier as the instructions had
included a specific shade number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it wasn’t until the day of the recital that I realized
neither my daughter nor I had ever actually applied either eyeliner or
lipstick.  These days you could probably find an instruction video
on-line, but this was pre-YouTube days.  We decided to tackle the
eyeliner first.  For those that don&#39;t know, an eyeliner pencil is
essentially a sharpened stick which you need to get really close to
the eye.  The entire concept seems barbaric and on my first attempt I
couldn’t bring myself to actually get right up next to her eye.  This
left her with a ring around her eye.  Knowing this wasn’t quite
correct I tried to fix it by coloring from the edge of the ring closer
in towards her eye.  Although in theory this worked, the end result
was far more goth than I had intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lipstick proved to be almost as challenging as the eyeliner,
although less dangerous.  To me, lipstick seems like a sticky crayon
and your lips have a natural line on them that separates them from the
rest of your face, so I figured if I just colored in between the lines
I would be good to go.  What I didn’t account for was that there is no
natural stopping point inside your mouth and I spent a good while in
front of the mirror making various lip poses trying to get a sense of
how far in I should color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dad!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this was sitting well with my daughter who was becoming more
and more panicked with each facial gesture.  After deciding on a
general plan I proceeded to put on the lipstick much like you would
color in a coloring book, with rapid back-and-forth type motion.
Again, although in theory this worked it left her with a very thick
layer of lipstick on her lips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, with the makeup done we rushed off to the dance recital.  I got
her checked in and took my seat in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recital started normally but it didn’t take long before the hot
overhead lights, heavy costumes and general physical activity started
to take their toll.  Like most of the dancers, my daughter started to
sweat … heavily.  This is apparently what waterproof eyeliner is for.
Without it the sweat mixed with the thick ring I had applied and
proceeded to run down her cheeks, giving her an Alice Cooper look.
Meanwhile, the lipstick I had applied in her mouth had been rubbing
against her teeth turning them a frightening shade of red and causing
her smile to take on a menacing grimace.  This added new meaning to
the dance as it appeared my daughter was melting into a nightmarish
black swan, threatening to eat the other dancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stuck in the audience I could only watch with mounting horror as the
thick layer of lipstick started to work itself outside her lips and
smear around her face.  My first thought was &amp;ldquo;my wife is going to kill
me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully some of the other moms took pity on her and tried to clean
her up between routines.  When my wife returned and saw the recital
photos she decided that she would never miss another dance recital
again.  My daughter recovered but has learned that dad is not who you
go to for makeup advice.  Still, whenever my kids ask me if they
should wear the blue outfit or the black one, I like to respond with
&amp;ldquo;now is that the darkest black one or the blackest black one?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
