<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vuejs | Hrakaroo</title>
    <link>/tags/vuejs/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/vuejs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Vuejs</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu82bb96251336236c27845c6dd2b93c07_14416_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Vuejs</title>
      <link>/tags/vuejs/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>One Seat Open</title>
      <link>/project/one-seat-open/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/one-seat-open/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oneseatopen.com&#34;&gt;One Seat Open&lt;/a&gt;, an invitation system for
limited seating events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project primarily came from a personal frustration in hosting my
own game nights.  Most invitation systems I researched were open ended
(no wait list support) or were so chock full of ads that I could
barely navigate them.  At the same time I was also looking for a
project with which to learn front end development as I have been
mostly focused backed development. So this seemed like a perfect
opportunity to build my own service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;development&#34;&gt;Development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After researching several frontend frameworks I eventually settled on
Vue.js with the Vuetify plugin for several reasons.  Vue.js was
established enough to have good tutorials, training videos and a
robust presence on Stack Overflow for questions.  It also had an easy
ramp up and it didn&amp;rsquo;t originate from Facebook.  (Petty, I know, but I
have a personal distain of Facebook).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;status&#34;&gt;Status&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November of 2019 I launched the site and moved hosting my game
night to the system so I can start &amp;ldquo;eating my own dog food.&amp;rdquo;  I still
have several large features I want to add before I really start
start trying to push it more globally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now I&amp;rsquo;m keeping it closed source, but free to use.  If the service
proves popular I will likely be forced to add either a for-pay section
or ads to cover my hosting fees, but otherwise I have no immediate
commercialization plans for the service.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
