<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Woodworking | Hrakaroo</title>
    <link>/categories/woodworking/</link>
      <atom:link href="/categories/woodworking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Woodworking</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu82bb96251336236c27845c6dd2b93c07_14416_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Woodworking</title>
      <link>/categories/woodworking/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>42 Inch Round Table in White Oak</title>
      <link>/post/white-oak-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/white-oak-table/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./table1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Table 1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last 20+ years we&amp;rsquo;ve had a 48 inch round dining room table in
our kitchen nook area. Like most folks, we ended up using this as our
primary table and while it was great it was always a bit over sized
for the space. Recently we were updating other parts of our house and
decided to finally replace the table with a 42 inch one.  In addition
to it being Six inches smaller, we also wanted one that felt less
bulky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We knew we wanted a solid hardwood table and we like the look of white
oak.  Most of the tables we found on-line were either super expensive
($3000+) or had straight or chunky legs which we didn&amp;rsquo;t love.  What we
wanted was something closer to our outdoor table which has legs that
curve in to a center ring and then out again. After some research I
decided to tackle the table myself. This was easily the biggest
project I&amp;rsquo;d done to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;design&#34;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./tableSketch.png&#34; alt=&#34;Table 1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using SketchUp Maker (2017) I worked up some designs until I had
something I was happy with.  I knew I wanted to curve the legs in, but
I wasn&amp;rsquo;t entirely sure how to do it.  My initial idea (which you can
sort of see in the sketch up) was to build the legs by laminating
three thinner boards together.  By overlapping them at the curve I
though I could build a strong joint.  I still think this is a good
design idea that would create a very strong curved leg, but in the end
I went with a more traditional joint and just use dowels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wood&#34;&gt;Wood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After making a cut list I went down to Crosscut Hardwoods and picked
up ~30 feet of 6/4 for the table top and ~15 feet of 8/4 for the legs.
The total cost for the wood was around $400.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I had the wood home I let it acclimate in my house for about a
week before milling it down.  While I do have a planer I don&amp;rsquo;t have a
jointer so I had to use a sled for the planer to get one side flat and
a simple jig for my table saw to get a straight edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;table-top&#34;&gt;Table Top&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finding an arrangement I liked for the top I glued the boards
together and let them dry overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I opted to not use any dowels or biscuits as they don&amp;rsquo;t really do much
for adding strength.  This proved to be a mistake as I didn&amp;rsquo;t get the
boards perfectly flush and after it dried I had to take a hand plane
and resurface both the top and bottom.  Next time I&amp;rsquo;m probably going
to put at least a couple of dowels in to assist with alignment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./glueUp.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Glue Up&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the top was dry I used a circle cutting jig and a spiral bit on
my plunge router to cut the circle. I only cut it 3/4 of the way down
before flipping the top over and using a flush trim bit on my trim
router to finish the circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t entirely sure how far to plunge cut before flipping the table
over.  Several of the videos I watched on this seemed to suggest you
only needed to make one or two passes with the router before flipping
the table over.  Thankfully I took it down further as my trim router
was barely able cut through what I had left.  In the future it&amp;rsquo;s
probably safer to take this down to 1/4 inch before flipping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./routedTop.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Routed Top&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;legs&#34;&gt;Legs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the legs I first used cardboard to try out several different
variations until I found something I liked.  Although I had my
sketchup design it helps to actually see it in person.  Plus, once I
had my cardboard template I was able to cut it at the joint (in the
middle of the curve) to figure out my rough cut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lining up the dowels for the joints was a process but everything came
together pretty well in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And yes, I used more glue than what is shown.  I had forgotten to
take a picture, so I stopped in the middle of my glue up to snap this
one.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clamping the legs proved more difficult than I anticipated.  I first
tried the trick of gluing cauls to some blue tape, but those popped
off pretty quickly when I started to tighten the clamps.  Thankfully I
had created some angle extensions that I was able to clap to the
individual pieces and then add an additional clap.  If I had to do it
over again I would plan this part out better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once set I built a simple jig so that I could make parallel cuts in
the top and bottom of the leg, as well as create the flat inner cut.
Using this I was able to get all four legs nearly identical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg3.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I made a router template from a piece of MDF I had lying around
and used it to cut the inner edge of each leg.  I did the same process
of only cutting part of the way through from the top, then removing
the template and flipping the piece over to cut the rest with the
flush trim bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg4.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 4&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally I cut the center joining pieces and created a lap joint for
them to fit together.  Then I glued up each set of legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg5.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 5&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sanding&#34;&gt;Sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came the sanding.  All in all I probably spent 2 full days
sanding everything.  I started with 80 grit sandpaper and took it all
the way up to 220 and used a wand light to make sure there were no
imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finish I was planning on using was Rubio Monocoat which actually
does not recommend going past 150 grit, so I then made one more pass
to bring it back down to 150.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related, although I like Rubio Monocoat, it is wildly expensive.  On
my next project I&amp;rsquo;m likely going to try to use Natura Onecoat as it
reportedly works similar to Rubio and is about half the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./sanding1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Sanding&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After testing out several different samples I ended up going with Pure
which, in retrospect, was probably a bit of a mistake.  I still really
like how the table looks, but its a little too honey colored for my
tastes.  I think something with a small percentage of white would have
offset the honey color, but its too late now and overall I&amp;rsquo;m pretty
happy with the way it turned out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./table2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Table 2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project took about two months to complete. I was mostly working
on it during the weekends and some evenings.  I did allow myself to
buy a planer for this project and I needed to buy a couple of router
bits as well.  So all included (wood, planer, router bits, Rubio
Monocoat, &amp;hellip;) I probably spent about $1200 in total on this project.
And while this is a lot, its still a far cry from the $3000 we were
seeing on-line and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty proud to have built this myself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
