<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Woodworking | Hrakaroo</title>
    <link>https://hrakaroo.com/category/woodworking/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://hrakaroo.com/category/woodworking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Woodworking</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://hrakaroo.com/media/icon_hu82bb96251336236c27845c6dd2b93c07_14416_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Woodworking</title>
      <link>https://hrakaroo.com/category/woodworking/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>42 Inch Round Table in White Oak</title>
      <link>https://hrakaroo.com/post/white-oak-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hrakaroo.com/post/white-oak-table/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./table1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Table 1&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last 20+ years we&amp;rsquo;ve had a 48 inch round dining room table in
our kitchen nook area. Like most folks, we ended up using this as our
primary table and while it was great it was always a bit over sized
for the space. Recently we were updating other parts of our house and
decided to finally replace the table with a 42 inch one.  In addition
to it being Six inches smaller, we also wanted one that felt less
bulky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six inches may not seem like a lot but if we multiply it out, a 48
inch table as a surface area of approximately 1809 inches squared
while a 42 inch table has a surface area of 1395 inches squared.
Thats a difference of 414 square inches, so almost three full
square feet smaller.  That is a fair bit and the new table feels
much smaller in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We knew we wanted a solid hardwood table and we liked the look of white
oak.  Most of the tables we found on-line were either super expensive
($3000+) or had straight or chunky legs which we didn&amp;rsquo;t love.  What we
wanted was something closer to our outdoor table which has legs that
curve into a center ring and then out again. After some research I
decided to tackle the table myself. This was easily the biggest
project I&amp;rsquo;d done to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;design&#34;&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./tableSketch.png&#34; alt=&#34;Table 1&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using SketchUp Maker (2017) I worked up some designs until I had
something I was happy with.  I knew I wanted to curve the legs in, but
I wasn&amp;rsquo;t entirely sure how to do it.  My initial idea (which you can
sort of see in the sketch up) was to build the legs by laminating
three thinner boards together.  By overlapping them at the curve I
thought I could build a strong joint.  I still think this is a good
design idea that would create a very strong curved leg, but in the end
I went with a more traditional joint and just used dowels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wood&#34;&gt;Wood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After making a cut list I went down to Crosscut Hardwoods and picked
up ~30 feet of 6/4 for the table top and ~15 feet of 8/4 for the legs.
The total cost for the wood was around $400.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I had the wood home I let it acclimate in my house for about a
week before milling it down.  While I do have a planer I don&amp;rsquo;t have a
jointer so I had to use a sled for the planer to get one side flat and
a simple jig for my table saw to get a straight edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;table-top&#34;&gt;Table Top&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After finding an arrangement I liked for the top I glued the boards
together and let them dry overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I opted to not use any dowels or biscuits as they don&amp;rsquo;t really do much
for adding strength.  This proved to be a mistake as I didn&amp;rsquo;t get the
boards perfectly flush and after it dried I had to take a hand plane
and resurface both the top and bottom.  Next time I&amp;rsquo;m probably going
to put at least a couple of dowels in to assist with alignment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./glueUp.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Glue Up&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the top was dry I used a circle cutting jig and a spiral bit on
my plunge router to cut the circle. I only cut it 3/4 of the way down
before flipping the top over and using a flush trim bit on my trim
router to finish the circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t entirely sure how far to plunge cut before flipping the table
over.  Several of the videos I watched on this seemed to suggest you
only needed to make one or two passes with the router before flipping
the table over.  Thankfully I took it down further as my trim router
was barely able to cut through what I had left.  In the future it&amp;rsquo;s
probably safer to take this down to 1/4 inch before flipping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./routedTop.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Routed Top&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;legs&#34;&gt;Legs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the legs I first used cardboard to try out several different
variations until I found something I liked.  Although I had my
sketchup design it helps to actually see it in person.  Plus, once I
had my cardboard template I was able to work backwards to figure out
how big my leg blanks needed to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this I took my cardboard template and cut it right where I
was picturing my joint to be.  Then I was able to flip over the top
piece and tape it back together which gave me an approximate template
for how big I needed to cut each leg blank.  Since I kept top and
bottom leg angles the same, the resulting template was now perfectly
straight and the taped cut line gave me the exact angle I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lining up the dowels for the joints was a process but everything came
together pretty well in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 1&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did have some concerns that the dowel joints might now be strong
enough as the pressure from the table to would basically be trying
to pry them apart. To counter act this I made sure that when I
jointed in my cross pieces that I used four dowels which really
locked in this joint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And yes, I used more glue than what is shown.  I had forgotten to
take a picture, so I stopped in the middle of my glue up to snap this
one.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clamping the legs proved more difficult than I anticipated.  I first
tried the trick of gluing cauls to some blue tape, but those popped
off pretty quickly when I started to tighten the clamps.  Thankfully I
had created some angle extensions that I was able to clamp to the
individual pieces and then add an additional clamp.  If I had to do it
over again I would plan this part out better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 2&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once set I built a simple jig so that I could make parallel cuts in
the top and bottom of the leg, as well as create the flat inner cut.
Using this I was able to get all four legs nearly identical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg3.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 3&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I made a router template from a piece of MDF I had lying around
and used it to cut the inner edge of each leg.  I did the same process
of only cutting part of the way through from the top, then removing
the template and flipping the piece over to cut the rest with the
flush trim bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg4.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 4&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally I cut the center joining pieces and created a lap joint for
them to fit together.  Then I glued up each set of legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./leg5.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Leg 5&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sanding&#34;&gt;Sanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came the sanding.  All in all I probably spent 2 full days
sanding everything.  I started with 80 grit sandpaper and took it all
the way up to 220 and used a wand light to make sure there were no
imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finish I was planning on using was Rubio Monocoat which actually
does not recommend going past 150 grit, so I then made one more pass
to bring it back down to 150.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related, although I like Rubio Monocoat, it is wildly expensive.  On
my next project I&amp;rsquo;m likely going to try to use Natura Onecoat as it
reportedly works similar to Rubio and is about half the cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./sanding1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Sanding&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mistake #5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After testing out several different samples I ended up going with Pure
which, in retrospect, was probably a bit of a mistake.  I still really
like how the table looks, but its a little too honey colored for my
tastes.  I think something with a small percentage of white would have
offset the honey color, but its too late now and overall I&amp;rsquo;m pretty
happy with the way it turned out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./table2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Table 2&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project took about two months to complete. I was mostly working
on it during the weekends and some evenings.  I did allow myself to
buy a planer for this project and I needed to buy a couple of router
bits as well.  So all included (wood, planer, router bits, Rubio
Monocoat, &amp;hellip;) I probably spent about $1200 in total on this project.
And while this is a lot, it&amp;rsquo;s still a far cry from the $3000 we were
seeing on-line and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty proud to have built this myself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a workshop in my garage</title>
      <link>https://hrakaroo.com/post/garage-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hrakaroo.com/post/garage-wall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted a small woodshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With both of my parents in theatre I spent a lot of my childhood in
the shop they used for building sets.  When we bought our first house
I purchased a couple of woodworking tools, but my work area was in the
garage which was shared with our cars.  This made it hard to work on
bigger projects and sawdust was always getting all over everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our second house had a three car garage which meant I finally
had a dedicated space, but sawdust control was still an issue.  Plus,
it rains a lot where I live so dampness control was also an issue,
especially as we went in and out of the garage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic hit I suddenly found myself in desperate need of a
project and decided to see if I could construct a wall between the
main garage and the third bay to create a small, dedicated woodshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the before picture.  Since the third bay was not isolated it
often became just a dumping ground for things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage1.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 1&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first step was to take all the sheetrock off the post.  Once I did
that I was pretty much committed to the project.  I knew I wanted
to use the post to divide the wall in half, structurally at least, and
I figured it would be better to work on the smaller half first, even though
it was going to have a door in it which, at the time, I had no idea
how to actually do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But first, I had to put in the header and footer boards to attach the
vertical 2x4s to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 2&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to nail into the concrete I bought a hammer drill to drill
anchor holes.  This worked, but for the other half of the wall I
borrowed a powder actuated nail gun from a friend of mine, which
basically uses a 22 cartridge to shoot a nail into the concrete.  Very
loud, but much faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage3.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 3&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage4.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 4&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage5.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 5&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the header and footer were attached I started putting in the vertical
2x4s. I read up a lot on how to build a door frame with a king stud, jack
stud and header plate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage6.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 6&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satisfied with the framing I went on to do the other side, using a
laser level to make sure the wall was straight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage7.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 7&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this side I wasn&amp;rsquo;t as lucky with the ceiling beams and they were
parallel with the wall instead of perpendicular, as they had been for
the first section.  This meant that I had to climb up in the attic
space and attach cross beams first before I could then attach the
header boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage8.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 8&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage9.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 9&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage10.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 10&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage11.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 11&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;insulation&#34;&gt;Insulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially I was not going to add insulation as I hate working with it.
If you don&amp;rsquo;t cover up enough you can get thousands of tiny glass
slivers that seem to take weeks to work their way out.  But in the end
I decided to add it, mostly because I was going to be running some
power tools and wanted the extra sound insulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage13.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 13&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also added in some 20amp outlets and ran all the wiring, but ended
up hiring an electrician to actually hook it into my electrical
panel.  I&amp;rsquo;ve added breakers to my panel before, but the whole thing
scares the hell out of me and is not something I wanted to do again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also installed a 240v 50amp circuit on the garage side for a future
electric car plug in, and a 240v 30amp circuit on the shop side for my
table saw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage14.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 14&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sheetrock&#34;&gt;Sheetrock&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I debated about installing the sheetrock myself or hiring out.
Although I&amp;rsquo;ve done some small patch repairs, I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually done a
full install before so this could be an opportunity to learn.  That
said, sheetrock is heavy and although I probably could have rigged up
something to help me install it, it is much faster as a two person
job.  So in the end I just hired out for this part as well.  We had
temporary access to a truck so I was able to pick up the sheets myself
and then two pros came in and got the whole thing installed and mudded
in less than a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage15.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 15&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage16.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 16&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage18.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 18&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage19.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 19&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;painting&#34;&gt;Painting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did decide to paint it myself so I started with primer and was
surprised at how much a new wall soaks in the primer.  I went through
&lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; more than I was expecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also opted to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; add any texture to the wall as most of the walls
in the garage were already pretty flat and I would have had to hire
out for the texture as well as I&amp;rsquo;ve heard it&amp;rsquo;s a trick to get right
the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage20.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 20&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;door&#34;&gt;Door&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had never hung a door before, but it turned out easier than I was
expecting.  In the three years since I installed this I still haven&amp;rsquo;t
had any issues with expansion or jamming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage21.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 21&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;moulding&#34;&gt;Moulding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I attached &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; of the moulding.  After going around the
door I got busy with other projects and still, as of this writing,
have not entirely finished the moulding.  Seeing as how we are now
modernizing the moulding in our house I may just wait and replace
this with the new moulding as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage22.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 22&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lights&#34;&gt;Lights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding lights was the last step.  There was already a plug in the
ceiling where a garage door opener could plug in, so I bought some
led strip lights and plugged them in with a remote on/off switch.
(Initially I was thinking I might actually wire up a switch, but
in the end this was easier and cheaper.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The led lights are fantastic and really do a great job of lighting up
the woodshop.  I have since pinned the wires to the ceiling so they
are no longer dangling down like you see here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./garage23.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Garage 23&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a fantastic project which I both super enjoyed working on,
and also left me with a very usable space for a woodshop.  I still
have a lot of work to do on organizing and building out the actual
shop, but having a dedicated space has been a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
