<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hiking | Hrakaroo</title>
    <link>/categories/hiking/</link>
      <atom:link href="/categories/hiking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Hiking</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu82bb96251336236c27845c6dd2b93c07_14416_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Hiking</title>
      <link>/categories/hiking/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiking around Mount St. Helens in 3&#43;1 Days</title>
      <link>/post/hiking-st-helens/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/hiking-st-helens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July 2019 my friend Tobin and I decided to hike the full Loowit
loop trail around Mount St. Helens. Both of us are experienced hikers
and in reasonable shape and figured we could probably complete about
10-14 miles a day. The total distance around the mountain is about
35 miles, so we figured it should take us approximately 3 days to
hike. We also managed to secure two passes to climb to the top of
St. Helens for Aug 2nd which extended our trip by one day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to climb to the top of Mount St. Helens you need a permit,
which can be difficult to obtain depending on when you want to climb.
The summer permits often sell out very quickly so initialy we assumed
we would not be able to climb to the top. Even so, we signed up on a
reseller web site and about a week before we were set to climb we were
contacted by someone who had two extra passes as some people in their
party backed out at the last moment. Further, the person lived in
Seattle and was only a short distance from Tobin, so two days before
we were set to leave Tobin drove to their house and bought the two
passes from the seller. The guy was really nice and didn&#39;t mark up
the cost and just charged us the $20 or so per pass that he had paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-trip&#34;&gt;The trip&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;where-to-start&#34;&gt;Where to start&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first challenge was figuring out where to enter the Loowit trail
and which direction to hike (clockwise or counter clockwise).  Since
there is only one trail up to the summit and our passes were for Aug
2nd we had a hard requirement of being near Monitor Ridge on the night
of Aug 1st. Initially we thought we would enter at Sheep Canyon
trailhead and hike clockwise on the trail.  This would put us around
Windy Pass on the first night and close to June Lake on the second
night.  (In retrospect this was probably not a great plan as Windy
Pass isn&#39;t named ironically.  It is windy as hell and camping there
would have been a trick.)  However, the &lt;em&gt;night before&lt;/em&gt; we were
planning on leaving we realized the trailhead we were going to use had
been washed out and we had to scramble to come up with a new plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new plan was to park at the Windy Ridge trailhead and hike counter
clockwise around the mountain.  Tobin is from Seattle and I&#39;m from
Portland so we met at Spiffy&#39;s at I-5 and Highway 12, stashed his car
in a gravel parking near the 76 gas station and drove my car to the
trailhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spiffy&#39;s is a bit of a dive restaurant off I-5 but there were not a
lot of other places around and we knew we wanted to get some take away
sandwiches.  I showed up first, walked in and started looking at the
menu.  While I was deciding an older guy with a &amp;ldquo;get off my lawn&amp;rdquo; look
to him walked in with a small lapdog in his arms.  The hostess
informed him that the dog would need to wait outside which cause him
to get really upset and he demanded/yelled that it was a &amp;ldquo;therapy
dog.&amp;rdquo;  The hostess wasn&#39;t having any of it and told him that he needed
a permit or some sort of license if it was a therapy dog. At that
point the guy yelled at the hostess &amp;ldquo;go fuck yourself you fucking
whore&amp;rdquo; and stormed out.  That was also the exact moment at which Tobin
walked into the restaurant and only heard the insult as the guy stored
out.  We looked at each other and both cracked up laughing as it was
such a bizarre way to start the trip.  To her credit, the hostess
handled it really well and the sandwiches were pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trail head is at the end of NF-99, super easy to find and there is
plenty of parking and a flush toilet bathroom. There are also some
interesting informational signs that talk about the eruption and slow
recovery of the area. We were a bit eager to get started so we didn&#39;t
linger too long. We ate the sandwiches we had picked up at Spiffy,
sunscreened up and headed off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Trailhead.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;trailhead&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our packs weighed around 24lbs and since Mount St. Helens is well
known for not having much water so each of us was also carrying close
to three liters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-1---122-miles&#34;&gt;Day 1 - 12.2 miles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./day1.png&#34; alt=&#34;day1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;starting&#34;&gt;Starting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first 1.7 miles the hike is along a winding gravel road. It&#39;s
blocked off from cars and well maintained, albeit not terribly
interesting.  At the end of the gravel road it&#39;s still another 1.2
miles until you actually connect to the Loowit trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./TobinJoshua.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tobin and Joshua&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we were hiking counter clockwise around the mountain we headed to
the right and started on the Loowit trail.  At this point the scenery
looks sort of like rolling hills with the mountain in the distance.
You can clearly see where the &amp;ldquo;blow out&amp;rdquo; was from the eruption but the
walking is pretty easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Starting.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;starting&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;loowit-falls&#34;&gt;Loowit Falls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around a mile into the trail there is a turn out to go see Loowit
Falls.  It&#39;s about 0.6 miles off the tail but well worth checking out.
Although you can &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; the falls, you can&#39;t actually get near it and
even getting down to the water is a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./LoowitFalls.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;loowit falls&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did meet up with a forest ranger just before we got to the turn off
for the falls and chatted with him a bit.  We asked the ranger if the
waterfall was worth the extra hike (as we had a long ways that
day).  His answer was something like &amp;ldquo;yeah, it&#39;s pretty good&amp;rdquo; which we
didn&#39;t find very convincing.  I think we even said, in a joking way,
&amp;ldquo;you are not exactly selling it here&amp;rdquo; to which he then responded very
excitedly &amp;ldquo;it&#39;s a 200 ft waterfall made of glacier melt coming out an
active Volcano!&amp;rdquo;  He was awesome and it totally convinced us to go,
and waterfall was amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we were back on the main trail it was another 0.8 miles until
Willow Springs.  Near Willow Springs there was actually water running
across the path and if we had needed water this would have been a
great place to fill up.  It was also the last time we would find water
until we stopped for camp that night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;restricted-zone&#34;&gt;Restricted Zone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Willow Springs the scenery gets significantly more barren and
rocky. This is also the recovery area so no camping is allowed and
really, it would have been hard to find a good spot to camp if we had
wanted. This goes on for 5.4 miles, but the trail is pretty easy to
see and mostly flat.  In a couple of places we did drift slightly off
the trail but thankfully others have erected rock piles that make
getting back on the trail pretty easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Restricted.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;restricted&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;castle-ridge&#34;&gt;Castle Ridge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you get close to Castle Ridge the scenery starts to change
dramatically.  The trail gets close to the ridge itself in sections
and it&#39;s a steep drop down.  Tobin also recognized Huckleberries so we
stopped at several big patches before continuing on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./CastleRidge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;castle ridge&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Castle Ridge it&#39;s 1.4 miles down to the Toutle River.  The start
of this section is a switch back on a sandy incline that could be
challenging to walk at time.  At times it could take a fair bit of
concentration but it wasn&#39;t impossible.  (I would not advise either
this section or the ridge for smaller children.)  After the sandy
incline you enter the forest and continue your switchbacks down.  It
was here that Tobin discovered wild Salmonberries within reach of the
trail and we were again stopping periodically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;toutle-river&#34;&gt;Toutle River&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last section down to the river itself is basically a steep cliff
for which the forest rangers have attached ropes for hikers to use.
It requires going down backwards, with your feet walking down the cliff
as you go hand over hand on the rope.  Once you get over the initial
shock it is actually rather easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./ToutleRope2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;toutle rope2&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./ToutleRope3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;toutle rope3&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./ToutleRiver.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;toutle river&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we were there the Toutle River was around 5 feet across and we
were able to cross easily by jumping across rocks.  We set up camp
next to the river and the sandy floor made for a really plush
ground. It was honestly one of the best night sleeps I&#39;ve ever had
camping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./ToutleRiver1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;toutle river&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were lots of places to set up our tents and when we arrived were
were the only people there, although another group did arrive just
before dusk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-2---102-miles&#34;&gt;Day 2 - 10.2 miles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./day2.png&#34; alt=&#34;day2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the morning we packed up, filled our water bottles and used the
ropes on the other side to climb out.  The path to climb out was
easier than the one to climb down and we probably could have managed
it without the rope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal was to hike down near the Summit trail, find a spot to camp
and hopefully water nearby.  The other campers at the river were
hiking the mountain in a clockwise direction and said they didn&#39;t see
any water other than June Lake. So our fall back plan was to find a
camping spot around the Summit trail, dump our packs and hike down to
June Lake for water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;crescent-ridge&#34;&gt;Crescent Ridge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right out of the river the hike is a brutal uphill climb that take you
from 3200 ft to 4700 ft in 1.7 miles.  It&#39;s almost entirely in the
trees so you don&#39;t get much of a view either.  We did stop to take a
couple of breaks on the hike up as we were still finding wild
Salmonberries and Huckleberries.  The Huckleberries especially were
perfectly ripe and really good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./TobinRelaxing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tobin Relaxing&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 1.5 miles after reaching the top of that climb the trail crosses
another ravine which again requires the use of attached ropes to climb in
and out of.  There was no water to cross in this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Rope1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;rope1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that the next 4 miles is a really nice and relaxing hike through
some beautiful scenery..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Day2Trail.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Trail&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, once we reached the trail for Summit Route we realized that
&amp;ldquo;finding a camping spot near by&amp;rdquo; was virtually impossible.  The trail
is really cut into a steep mountain side and the flora is pretty thick
on either side of the trail.  We either had to hike back a mile or so
to where there was some flat areas to camp, or hike forward and hope
it flattened out.  Hiking back would have taken us further away from
water so we decided to go forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;chocolate-falls&#34;&gt;Chocolate Falls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly two miles from Sumit Route is Chocolate Falls and
decided to make camp there as there are plenty of flat areas nearby
just before you cross over the falls. However, if you venture a little
ways towards the cliff (and away from the falls) you will find a
really nice circular camping area, complete with a fire pit (which we
did not use).  However, being so far off the path was really nice as
we were not bothered at all by people passing on the trail and we felt
secure about leaving our stuff there while we hiked to the summit the
next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./ChocolateCamp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;chocolate camp&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chocolate Falls is named as such because the water contains a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of
sediment and takes on a chocolate milk color/consistency.  But there
was water and by straining it through a bandana and our Sawyer squeeze
bag we were able to filter it enough to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./ChocolateFalls1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;chocolate falls1&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./ChocolateFalls2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;chocolate falls2&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./ChocolateFalls3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;chocolate falls3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the bandana was not part of our inital plan but the water had a
lot of silt in it and Tobin had a brand new bandana with him.
Regretfully the bandana was red and had probably only been washed once
so when we were straining the water it took on a very pink color.
Even after using the Sawyer squeeze bag it still had a bit of a
pinkish hue to it, but it didn&#39;t seem to contribute any taste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-3---82-miles---the-summit&#34;&gt;Day 3 - 8.2 miles - The Summit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./day3.png&#34; alt=&#34;day3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until now our weather had been perfect but the this morning it was
raining.  We had initially thought we would start on our summit hike
at 8am, but the rain was coming down hard enough that we just stayed
in our tents for a couple of hours to see if it would clear.  By 11am the
rain was starting to let up enough so we decided to get going before
it was too late.  Both of us took our backpacks but only bought with us
some food, water, warm clothes and our permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now had to backtrack the two miles back to the Summit Route.  This
was mostly uphill and because of the rain we were getting soaked every time
we brushed up against the plants on the sides of the trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;summit-ridge&#34;&gt;Summit Ridge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./SummitRoute1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;summit route1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not an easy hike.  The very start of this path is like a
normal, albeit steep, trail but it quickly turns into climbing over
volcanic boulders.  There isn&#39;t really a trail to follow anymore, but
the route is marked by posts which are placed just close enough
together that you can just see the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./SummitRoute2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;summit route2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We passed a couple of people coming down who had gone up very early
that morning and mentioned that the entire top of the mountain was
pretty well fogged in and there was not much to see.  Still, we were
determined and continued up. The entire hike is about 2.1 miles, but
it is very slow going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./SummitRoute3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;summit route3&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 2/3rds of the way up we met a forest ranger who told us that
&amp;ldquo;there is a crack at the rim and it appears that a section is about to
fall in,&amp;rdquo; so we should stay back several meters from the edge.  He
also mentioned that because of the weather he was guessing that of the
100 passes that were issued for that day, probably about 20 of them
were going to actually be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pumice-path&#34;&gt;Pumice Path&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As hard as the hike was so far, the pumice path that is at the end is
even harder.  The incline is very steep and with every step up you
take you slip back down almost a half a step.  It&#39;s like this for
almost half a mile and the pumice easily doubles the distance. There
is also not a clear visual for how far you still have to go so it can
seem a bit unending at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-top&#34;&gt;The top&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Summit1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;summit 1&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./Summit2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;summit 2&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./Summit3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;summit 3&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./View.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;view&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good thing about waiting those three hours before leaving camp is
that by the time we did reach the top the clouds were clearing and we
could see all around the mountain.  Unfortunately, the clouds &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; the
crater did not clear so we never really got a good full look inside,
although from time to time we got a couple of good glimpses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Crater.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;cater&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise the view from the top is really amazing and I&#39;m glad we made
the trip.  We did walk partway around the edge and we did see the
crack the ranger was talking about.  Because of the scale of
everything, looking over the edge didn&#39;t seem like a huge drop, but
apparently its something like a 2600 ft drop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending about 30 mins at the top we headed down which gives you
a totally new perspective on just how far you have climbed and how
much on a ridge you really are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time we reached our camp at Chocolate Falls it was getting
dark.  We decided to grab some more water but then ended up just
leaving it in our bottles so we could filter it the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day 4 - 12.3 miles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./day4.png&#34; alt=&#34;day4&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning we were awaken by the sounds of runners going down
the trail.  It turns out that there were several races going on that
day, with one of them being a full run around the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also turns out that Chocolate Falls does not normally run in the
mornings as it needs the afternoon sun to melt the snow.  So it was
really fortunate we had collected water the night before as it was
totally dry that morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a 1.2 mile hike to the cut off for June Lake and shortly past
that past a creek that was flowing and allowed us to get more water.
This water was clear and didn&#39;t need to be double filtered.  After
that it was 4.8 miles to Pumice Butte.  The hike was really beautiful
and you can see several other mountains in the distance.  We stopped
often for Huckleberries and the very occasional Salmonberry and to move
off the path at times for runners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Trail1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Trail2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Trail3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Trail4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pumice-butte&#34;&gt;Pumice Butte&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several people claim you can get water near Pumice Butte but all the
water we saw was very stagnant and didn&#39;t look good at all.  The 1.8
miles of The Plains of Abraham are flat, long and because of the time
of day we were there, very hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Flats1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Flats2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Flats3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the Flats we could have opted to take a short cut back
to the car (and my feet were killing me by this point), or we could
continue on the Loowit trail and complete the full loop.  We opted to
complete the full loop and just before we headed up Windy pass we
crossed a running creek and were able to fill up on water one last
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;windy-pass&#34;&gt;Windy pass&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The climb over Windy pass was harder than I was expecting as you have
a steep climb up, and short jog forward and then a steep switchback
back down.  Also, deceptively, they have put posts that run up to the
left, giving the impression you have to climb much higher than you
actually do.  I&#39;m not sure if this was someones idea of a joke or if
there is another trail up that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;WindyPass.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case we made it down and eventually made it back to the spot
where we first started on the Loowit trail.  From there it was 2.5
miles back to the car and by now we were feeling every step of it.
Also the winding gravel road has several false turns where you can
easily fall into thinking that the car is &amp;ldquo;just ahead&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-car&#34;&gt;The car&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the car we changed into clean(er) clothes and headed
back to Tobins car, stopping off at Plaza Jalisco&#39;s Mexican restaurant
for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;retrospective&#34;&gt;Retrospective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;equipment&#34;&gt;Equipment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;boots&#34;&gt;Boots&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tobin was wearing hiking shoes while I was wearing hiking boots.
Although my boots did better when it was wet, and when we were
climbing over the boulders, I think in the long run wearing hiking
shoes would have been a better call.  They are lighter and since we
were on a trail for a majority of the time I think the boots were,
perhaps, overkill.  And by the last day, especially that last 2.5
miles, my feet were killing me.  Tobin commented that his feet hurt as
well, but I think the boots were adding to my discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;socks&#34;&gt;Socks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should have brought more socks.  In the past when I&#39;ve hiked for a
couple of days (2-4) I usually bring just two pairs of socks, but for
those hikes I&#39;m often spending the day at the destination or wearing
my camp shoes. For this trip we were hiking every day and it would
have been really nice to put on a clean pair of socks every moring.
Tobin washed his out in the river which seems to have helped, but
really I just think at least one pair of socks a day is the minimum
and perhaps two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;camera&#34;&gt;Camera&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tobin and I both brought cameras with us, but while I just brought my
cell phone (because, hey, it has a camera in it) Tobin brought an
actual digital camera.  However, since I had my phone off for the
majority of the trip, taking a picture meant that I had to stop, take
out my phone, wait for it to turn on, take a picture and then shut it
down and put it away again.  Tobin, on the other hand, had a handy
pouch on his belt and was able to quickly take out his camera to take
pictures.  I had thought that non-SLR digital cameras were a thing
of the past, but after this trip I now included a digital camera in my
packing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;water&#34;&gt;Water&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the camera, Tobin&#39;s backpack also enabled him to carry at
least one liter of water where he could easily reach and drink from
it.  Mine was attached to the back of my backpack making it a pain and
often I had to ask Tobin to get my water for me.  As a consequence I
probably drank less than I should have.  I need to either figure out a
better way to hook up a bottle, or get one of those camel packs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;more-space&#34;&gt;More space&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had brought with me some fleece pants and a fleece top and while
these don&#39;t weigh much, they do take up a fair bit of space.  Weight
wasn&#39;t really an issue on this trip, but space was.  As it was, my bag
was packed really tight which required extra time packing up in the
morning and trying to get to anything in my pack.  Since this trip I
have replaced some of the gear in my pack with things that just take
up less space so I can treat my bag as more of a simple stuff sack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;bivy-or-tent&#34;&gt;Bivy or Tent&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really like sleeping in a bivy but at the last moment I decided to
swap my bivy for a tent which I feel was a good call.  I like using a
bivy because they are fast to set up and overall just more fun.
However, on this trip it would have been miserable sleeping in the
bivy when it was raining and the 3 hours we hung out in the tent
before climbing to the summit.  I&#39;m also not sure I would have been as
keen on leaving my bivy out when we were hiking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;sleeping-pad&#34;&gt;Sleeping pad&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a blow up air pad while Tobin had the waffle mat.  I think the
air pad is more comfortable, but you do run the risk that it could
rupture and then you can be in some real trouble.  I did have a small
patch kit with me, but I&#39;ve never used it and I&#39;m not sure how well it
would work if I had to patch my air pad at night.  Additionally, the
air pad is noisy as hell when you move around on it.  It makes a sound
that is similar to rubbing a balloon. For next season I think I&#39;m going
to try using a waffle pad and see how that works.  I also like that
the set up for the waffle pad is super quick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;hiking-gloves&#34;&gt;Hiking gloves&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t have a good pair of hiking gloves with me and I really wish I
did.  I did have some fingerless gloves (aka hobo gloves) which
convert to mittens, and while they were warm enough they were not the
best for climbing with.  Ultimately I need to get a good pair of
gloves that are warm enough for the evenings, but also rugged enough
to climb over boulders with.  Or, if no such glove exists, then
perhaps two pairs, one for warmth and one for climbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;folding-chair&#34;&gt;Folding chair&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also added to my bag a folding chair.  Yeah, I could just sit
on stones and trees and the such, but after a long day, and in the
morning, it is nice to be able to sit on a real chair.  Sitting on the
stones and logs meant that I was constantly trying to find a
comfortable one or leaning to the side as I am sitting.  The new
folding chairs are down around a pound now so I&#39;m hoping to try this
out on my next hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;sawyer-squeeze-bottles&#34;&gt;Sawyer squeeze bottles&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These things are awesome.  When we got home and cleaned it out it was
amazing how brown the water was and how much they filtered things.
They are awesome, I just wanted to point that out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hike&#34;&gt;Hike&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;bugs&#34;&gt;Bugs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally I&#39;m bothered by mosquitoes but I don&#39;t think we encountered
any on this trip.  Perhaps this is due to the general lack of
water but even the flies were not that bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;overall&#34;&gt;Overall&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all we had a fantastic time and hiked a total of 42.9 miles.
The changes in the scenery were really interesting and the rope climbs
and wild berries made for an interesting trek. Even though we had to
scramble to find an alternative, I really think entering at Windy Pass
and working counter clockwise worked out well for us.  The only
disappointment was that the weather wasn&#39;t clearer when we were at the
top, but it just means we will have to return sometime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;forest-rangers&#34;&gt;Forest Rangers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, I want to give special thanks to the awesome forest
rangers we met along the way.  They are super fun to talk with and a
treasure trove of information. They are also the ones that go through
each year and set the ropes so you can climb down and up the cliffs.
So thank you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
